[Music]
Hi everyone, this is Ravi. Welcome to
Tricentes Taska mobile automation
tutorial. As you all know, I have
already published four YouTube videos
related to mobile automation by using
Tricentis Taska. As part of those four
YouTube videos, I have explained you how
can we get started with Tricentis mobile
agent and what are all the different
features that are available in Tricentis
mobile agent console. And in lesson two
I have explained you how can we set up
Android emulators and how can we install
and download the Android Studio. And in
lesson three we have prepared and
connected the Android mobile device via
USB and also via Wi-Fi. And then in
previous lesson I've showed you how can
we scan Android mobile application by
using mobile engine with tricentis
taska. So this is our lesson five where
I'm going to teach you how can we
automate our first mobile test case for
Android devices.
The agenda for today's session is I'm
going to show you how can we create
mobile test case to automate using
tricentis tasks. I'm going to show you
how can we use standard modules from
mobile engine while automating your test
cases and we are going to take help of
the configurations related to
connections and the applications that we
have established in our previous
session. So I would recommend you guys
to visit lesson 4 before you watch this
session and then we are going to use
above preconfigured values which are
coming from connections and applications
during test case automation. So now
without delay let us jump onto the
system and let us automate our first
mobile test case by using tricentis
taska. So this is my tricus taska. So in
my previous lesson I've showed you how
can we scan the elements of a mobile
native application by using tricentis
taska. When we are scanning the
application like tip calculator in our
case we have scanned the elements of
native application called tip
calculator. So when we are scanning the
application we have performed some
configurations. So we have established
the connection by using local or remote
connectivity and also we have added the
device and then we have also added the
application that we would like to scan
and then we have scanned the elements of
the application. So these are the
elements that we scanned in our previous
lesson. As we scanned the application by
using local connection and the device
Samsung. So there are some
configurations
that were created automatically by
tricentis task. What are those
configurations? Go to your project
and then expand this particular
configurations.
Under configurations, expand mobile
section where you can see two
configurations. One is applications,
another one is connections.
Applications showing you the tip
calculator application because we have
scanned the elements of tip calculator.
That's why the configurations
are created automatically by
tricentistoska while scanning the
application.
And another configuration is
connections. So if you expand these
connections, you can see a connection is
already established. What are the
connections? We have local connection as
well as remote connection. So either you
can use local connection or you can use
remote connection. For both of them
there are some configurations that were
automatically saved in trictoka while
scanning the application. So I'm going
to use these two configurations
application related configurations and
connection related configurations
while automating my test case. So these
configurations are very important. Now
let us go to test case section to create
the test case.
So under test case section right click
on test case folder and create a
subfolder called mobile automation.
Under this folder I'm going to create my
first test case. Right click on this
folder and create test case. I'm going
to name this as tip calculator
basic test
and this is my test case name. Now
as soon as you create the test case,
double click on this test case. One
important thing is you need to
configure the test configuration
parameters. We need to first provide the
test configuration parameters. How can
you go to test configuration parameters?
Select the test case. Under test case,
there are three different tabs. Details,
test configurations, control flow
diagram. So you need to navigate to test
configuration. So here
I need to now create the test
configurations for my mobile testing.
How can we create that? For that, let's
drag this mobile automation project and
put it at the right side. Okay, let me
close the module section here.
Now in the left side,
left side I have test case section,
right side I have project tab. Under
project tab, I have configurations.
Right? So now first I would like to use
my application configurations. What is
the application that we are automating?
Tip calculator is the application. So
now I'm going to drag these
configurations and drop onto my test
case configurations.
So as I explained you earlier these
configurations
are created
while scanning our elements
by using tricentistoska in our previous
lesson. Refer my lesson four. So this is
my application related configuration
which shows application ID and some
other inheritant properties. Okay. like
application ID, application platform and
application type. Apart from application
configurations,
I'll be using the connections
configurations as well. So in my case, I
would like to use remote connection
because my Samsung device is connected
to my remote machine. I'm going to drag
and drop the connection related
configurations onto my test case
configurations.
So if you see here this is my remote
connection. This is my PMA server that
is
tricentis mobile agent server and then
type is TMA.
Okay. So these two configurations you
need to map to the test case before even
you start automating the test case
because these are the preconditions for
you to execute your test case
on mobile device which is connected to
your tricantis mobile agent. Apart from
these two configurations,
there is another test configuration that
you need to set that is device name.
Right click on this create a new test
configuration parameter.
As soon as I type device, it is
prepopulating the device name. Right?
Select the device name. And what is your
device name? My device name is a unique
ID of your device. Where can I see that
unique ID? I can see the unique ID in my
Tricentis mobile agent. For that go to
your tricentis mobile agent right click
open console and then here scroll down
and click on configure devices. So this
is a device which is connected to my
remote machine. If you see here there is
a field called UD ID. This represents
your unique ID for your device. If you
have multiple devices, the UD ID will be
unique for each device. So for my
device, this is my UD ID. Copy this one.
And you need to provide this UD ID as
device name. Paste it here. So this is
my device name. And now save the test
case. So what we have done we have first
created an empty test case and then for
this test case we have created some test
configurations. What are those? I have
mapped the application related test
configuration which is tip calculator
test configuration by dragging and
dropping onto test configurations and
then I have also
mapped the connections related
configurations I have dragged and
dropped onto my tip calculator basic
test configuration test case right and
then I also created a new TCP test
configuration parameter called device
name and the name I have copied from
Tyentis mobile agent console. I have
copied UD ID and I pasted the same UD ID
here. So here we have completed all test
configuration related steps. Now our
next step is to automate the test case.
Now to open any application to open
native application in your mobile you
need to use a standard module. What is
that standard module? Let's open module
section
and here go to standard modules.
Expand Tbox Engine and then go to your
mobile. Under mobile
you can see one standard module called
open mobile application.
So whenever you automate your mobile
related test cases this will be your
first step. You need to use open mobile
app standard module. Okay. So let's
close this one. So to add the open
mobile app
standard module you can add from here
also. How can I do that? Right click on
this test case
search and add test step. Here I can
type open mobile app. So this is my open
mobile app. Select that one.
Here under application you need to
provide the full path of application
or you can directly use your test
configuration. So if you see here the
test configuration related to
application is already created while
scanning our application. So I would
like to use this test configuration
parameter. What is that application ID?
because this application ID consists of
the full path of my APK file. So here
to use your test configurations
you need to create you need to open
curly braces CP and then
CP open square braces and you can see
here all the test configurations
whatever we created here are showing
you. So here I'm going to select
application ID.
Application ID. So this is my test
configuration. Close square braces and
close curly braces. So this is my
application ID which is coming from my
test configurations. So once I open the
application, what is my next step? My
next step is to perform action. What is
that? So let me show you what I'm going
to do here. First, I'm going to open
the tip calculator.
So, this is my tip calculator. Once I
open the tip calculator, I need to enter
the base price. And then once I enter
the base price based on the tip, it's
going to calculate the total price. I
need to verify this total price. So,
that is the scenario that we would like
to automate. And we have already scanned
the related objects or elements in our
previous lesson. I'm going to use the
same elements now. Okay, for that let's
open module and let's keep this module
aside. Okay, what I'm going to do bring
it to right side. Okay, now I would like
to use the same module that we scanned
earlier. So what I'm doing now I'm
dragging and dropping onto my test case.
So now once I open the application here
I'm going to name this step as
validate the total price.
So here under base text box I need to
enter 2,00. So here I'm going to say
2,00 and my action mode should be input.
So once that is done now I would like to
calculate the total price here. So my
total price is 2,300
but here I would like to use the action
mode as verify because I'm calculating
the total price including the tip right
and now save your test case. So what I
want to do so now what I would like to
do I would like to run this particular
test case and see if it works correctly.
So now so now let me run this particular
test case. Right click and
run in scratchbook. Let's open the
mobile here. So you can see what are all
the actions that is performed by tricasa
in mobile screen and right side mobile
mirror. So now see it is installing the
APK file first
calculator APK file. Now it opened the
APK and it entered 2,00 and now it is
calculating total price 2300. Let's see
why the test case got failed. Okay,
let's open this one. It says your total
price is
expected value is 2,300 but actually is
2,300. 0. So let me do one thing. Let me
change the value to 0 0. Okay, let's
save the test case. And now again let me
run the test case one more time. Right
click and run in scratchbook. So
whenever you run the test case, it
always
installs the APK file first and then it
performs the test case actions.
So now enter 2,00 validate the total
price. Now it should pass. So now you
can see your test case is passed. So
here I have entered the value and now
expected value is 2,300 and your actual
value is 2,300.
So we are able to validate or we are
able to interact with my Samsung mobile
device and I'm able to open the native
application and I'm able to interact
with that native application to perform
some actions and to validate my test
case.
So in the same way if you are using any
virtual device
as I explained you in my lesson two or
lesson three if you are using Android
Studio and if you created Android
virtual device it's going to show
Android virtual device as well along
with your Samsung real device right
the only change what you need to make is
if you want to interact with some other
device you just need to change your UD
ID. If you go here now into the triccent
all the configurations remain same but
your device name is going to change. So
let me do one thing. Let me execute the
same test case in Android Studio or in
Android virtual device instead of my
real Samsung device. So this is my
Android Studio. Let us go to Android
virtual device manager. I have explained
you all these things in my previous
lessons. Now let me
so let me start my first virtual device.
Let's run this virtual device.
So this is my Android emulator or my
Android virtual device. So this is my
pixel virtual device. So now to run my
test cases in Android emulator or
virtual device all we need to do is let
us open tricentis mobile agent. So now
you can see there are two mobiles that
are displaying here. One is my previous
real device and another one is you can
see medium phone ravi API. So if you see
my virtual device name also medium phone
ravi API. So that means I can see two
mobile devices in my tricentis mobile
agent. Now what is my unique ID for this
virtual device? So this is my unique ID.
Copy this one. And now let's go to
tricantis taska. Here I would like to
change the device name to emulator
54. This is my emulator unique ID. So if
I run the test case now, right click and
run in scratchbook. Now your test case
should run on Android emulator. So let
us see how it works.
So you can see here it is installing APK
file and then it should open your tip
calculator application.
Yes. So it is entering the value 2,00
and now it is validating the total
price.
So you can see here our test steps are
passed. You can see my total price is
2,300 and actual price is 2,300. So that
means we are able to execute our test
case in Android emulator as well as we
were able to execute our test case in
Samsung real device as well. So if you
have any queries leave your queries in
the comment box. I'll try to respond to
your queries.
Thank you.
Hope you all understand today's
concepts. How can we automate our first
mobile test case for Android device
where we have created a new test case
and then we have performed the test case
configuration parameters. We have
actually mapped the connections and the
application configurations that we
created while scanning the modules in
our earlier lesson. And then once we
complete the test case configurations,
then we have automated our test case by
using standard modules and the modules
that we have scanned in earlier session.
Please do subscribe to the channel.
Click on bell icon. You'll receive
notifications whenever I publish more
videos. Don't forget to like and share
the video. Thank you.
[Music]